<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Adrian Galdran - Research Site on Adrian Galdran - Research Site</title>
    <link>https://agaldran.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Adrian Galdran - Research Site on Adrian Galdran - Research Site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Adrian Galdran</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>DACO - Practical Lecture 1 - Introduction to Python for Scientific Computing</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_1/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE: This tutorial is under construction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year we have decided to move from Matlab to Python for the practical sessions.
Some of you maybe will not have worked with this programming language.
This first lecture is intended to guide you through your first steps in this programming language,
and make you aware of the (super-rich) Python ecosystem for scientific computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really hope that by the end of this course you will be a Python fan, and consider abandoning Matlab once and forever!
This is an overview of what you will be learning today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motivation and Goals. What is Python?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python Installation. Accompanying Tools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anaconda Python Distribution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Executing Python code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction to the Python Programming Language&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fundamental Python data types&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything is an object&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python Modules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python Basic Operators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sequences and Object Containers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python typing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flow Control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python Functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classes and Object-Oriented Programming
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complementary Python Scientific Computing Tools: Numpy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction to NumPy Arrays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slicing NumPy Arrays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indexing NumPy Arrays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other numpy arrays manipulation techniques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complementary Python Scientific Computing Tools: Matplotlib&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic Matplotlib usage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plot Customization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Homework 😱&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources and References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So&amp;hellip; let&amp;rsquo;s move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-motivation-and-goals-what-is-python&#34;&gt;1.- &lt;strong&gt;Motivation and Goals. What is Python?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First thing, Python is &lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt;. Second, it is &lt;strong&gt;simple&lt;/strong&gt;.
Third, it is increasingly becoming the tool of choice for data science projects.
Fourth, it&amp;rsquo;s multi-platform, it can run in Windows, Linux, Mac, your mobile phone&amp;hellip;
And last, there is a &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt; community of contributors to lots of open-source projects that complement it.
This manifests in the form of a large ecosystem of scientific computing tools that grow along with the number of users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, to add all this to your tool-belt, the first step is to familiarize yourself with the Python language itself.
Today we will quickly review the main notions to get started on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, let us install Python!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-python-installation-accompanying-tools&#34;&gt;2. &lt;strong&gt;Python Installation. Accompanying tools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-1-anaconda-python-distribution&#34;&gt;2.1 Anaconda Python Distribution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this course we will use the Python language programming.
However, as mentioned above, one of the main strengths of Python is the large amount of available scientific libraries.
This means that, together with the core Python language, we&amp;rsquo;ll be using several Python packages to perform scientific computations.
But instead of installing all these packages manually one at a time, we will be using a &lt;strong&gt;Python distribution&lt;/strong&gt;.
A distribution consists of the core Python package and several hundred modules, and available through a single download and installation.
In this course, we will use the Anaconda Python distribution.
Apart of Python itself and several hundred libraries, Anaconda also includes two very useful development environments: &lt;strong&gt;Jupyter NB&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Spyder&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spyder&lt;/strong&gt; is a Matlab-like &lt;strong&gt;IDE&lt;/strong&gt; (Integrated Development Environment) that we will be using for complex/long programming assignments.
On the other hand, &lt;strong&gt;Jupyter NB&lt;/strong&gt; is a functionality that allows you to run sequentially code in your browser.
I will be giving you instructions in class on how to install and use both tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Anaconda Python distribution can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.continuum.io/downloads&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Please install Python 3.
For windows users, if you are finding troubles, let me know asap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-2-executing-python-code&#34;&gt;2.2  Executing Python code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python has two different modes: &lt;strong&gt;interactive&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;standard&lt;/strong&gt;.
The interactive mode is meant for experimenting your code one line or one expression at a time.
The standard mode is useful for running programs from start to finish.
You will probably find yourself alternating between both modes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-2-1-python-interactive-mode&#34;&gt;2.2.1 Python Interactive Mode&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a first example on interactive mode, open a command console, type &lt;code&gt;python&lt;/code&gt;, and you will start using Python. Experiment a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more convenient way of building code interactively is through &lt;strong&gt;Jupyter iPython notebooks&lt;/strong&gt;.
This also allows us to mix text, code, and maths, which is really cool.
To start an iPython notebook, open a console, type jupyter notebook, and navigate in your browser to &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:8888/&lt;/code&gt;.
In windows, you may need a log-in password, provided automatically after executing jupyter.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dataquest.io/blog/jupyter-notebook-tips-tricks-shortcuts/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; you can find a series of useful tricks and shortcuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-2-2-python-standard-mode&#34;&gt;2.2.2 Python Standard Mode&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, we write a text file with Python instructions, and run it. &lt;code&gt;hello_world.py&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, there is a more convenient way for building code in standard mode, which is using an IDE.
This programming tool will allow you to more easily debug, inspect variables, and quickly modify your code.
They typically also include an embedded interactive system. An example of an IDE is &lt;strong&gt;Spyder&lt;/strong&gt;, already contained in the Anaconda distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For the contents of this lecture, starting from Section 3, a notebook version of this lecture is available in a static
view &lt;a href=&#34;http://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/agaldran/daco_2017_practicals/blob/master/lecture_1_python/PL1_introduction2Python.ipynb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
Please click the download button in the right top corner, download and open it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-introduction-to-the-python-programming-language&#34;&gt;3. &lt;strong&gt;Introduction to the Python Programming Language&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-1-fundamental-python-data-types&#34;&gt;3.1 - Fundamental Python data types&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python contains several typical built-in data types as part of the core language.
The same as in e.g Matlab (and different from e.g. C) you do not need to explicitly declare the type of a variable.
Python determines data type of variables by how they are used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, to create an integer (&lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt;) variable you simply type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# An integer variable a
a = 5
print(type(a))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other basic/common python types are for instance &lt;code&gt;float&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;string&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;boolean&lt;/code&gt;, exemplified below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# A float variable f
f = 5.0
# A boolean
b = True
# A string
c = &#39;bom dia&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-2-everything-is-an-object&#34;&gt;3.2 - Everything is an object&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important that you start thinking of the above examples &lt;code&gt;a,f,b,c&lt;/code&gt; as &lt;strong&gt;objects&lt;/strong&gt;.
Each object in Python has three characteristics: object &lt;strong&gt;type&lt;/strong&gt;, object &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt;, and object &lt;strong&gt;identity&lt;/strong&gt;.
Object &lt;strong&gt;type&lt;/strong&gt; tells Python what kind of an object it&amp;rsquo;s dealing with.
A type could be a number, or a string, or a list, or something else.
Object &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt; is the data value is contained by the object.
This could be a specific number, for example.
Finally, you can think of object &lt;strong&gt;identity&lt;/strong&gt; as an identity number for the object.
Each distinct object in the computer&amp;rsquo;s memory will have its own identity number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Python objects have either data or functions or both associated with them.
These are known as &lt;strong&gt;attributes&lt;/strong&gt;.
The name of the attribute follows the name of the object, and they are separated by a dot in between them.
The two types of attributes are called either &lt;strong&gt;data attributes&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;methods&lt;/strong&gt;.
A data attribute is a value that is attached to a specific object.
In contrast, a method is a function that is attached to an object.
And typically a method performs some function or some operation on that object.
Object type always determines the kind of operations that it supports.
In other words, depending on the type of the object,
different methods may be available to you as a programmer.
Finally, an &lt;strong&gt;instance&lt;/strong&gt; is one occurrence of an object.
For example, you could have two strings.
They may have different values stored in them,
but they nevertheless support the same set of methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-3-python-modules&#34;&gt;3.3 - Python Modules&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python contains builtin functions, such as &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; that can be used by all Python programs.
However, while the Python library consists of all core elements, such as data types and built-in functions,
the bulk of the Python library consists of &lt;strong&gt;modules&lt;/strong&gt;.
In order for you to be able to make use of modules in your own code,
you first need to import those modules using the &lt;code&gt;import&lt;/code&gt; statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example of modules, attributes, methods, in numpy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numpy example above made available some specific data types and methods for us.
This is an example of a &lt;strong&gt;Python module&lt;/strong&gt;.
In general, Python modules are libraries of code that you import and use through &lt;code&gt;import&lt;/code&gt; statements.
Let&amp;rsquo;s go through a simple example. Import the &lt;code&gt;math&lt;/code&gt; module.
This module gives you access to the pi constant. Print its value.
This module also gives you access to several mathematical operations. Find out (print) the value of the sine of pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you only need, e.g., the value of pi from the entire &lt;code&gt;math&lt;/code&gt; module, you can import it selectively:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;from math import pi
print(pi)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-4-python-basic-operators&#34;&gt;3.4 - Python Basic Operators:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operators are symbols that allow you to use logic and arithmetic in your computations.
Python has several operators, the most prominent ones being &lt;strong&gt;arithmetic&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;comparison&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;logical&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-4-1-arithmetic-operators&#34;&gt;3.4.1 - Arithmetic operators:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will take two variables and perform simple mathematical operations on them.
They are addition &lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt;, subtraction &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt;, multiplication &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt;, division &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;, modulus &lt;code&gt;%&lt;/code&gt;, floor division &lt;code&gt;//&lt;/code&gt;, and exponentiation &lt;code&gt;**&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;print(3+2, 3-2, 3*2, 3/2, 3%2, 3//2, 3**2)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-4-2-comparison-operators&#34;&gt;3.4.2 - Comparison operators:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They observe two variables and return a boolean value.
They are the usual greater than (&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/code&gt;), equal (&lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt;), different (&lt;code&gt;!=&lt;/code&gt;), and lower than (&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/code&gt;) mathematical operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;print(3&amp;gt;2, 3&amp;lt;2, 3==2, 3!=2, 3&amp;gt;=2, 3&amp;lt;=2)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-4-3-logical-operators&#34;&gt;3.4.3 - Logical operators:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These operators will interpret their input as boolean values, and return a boolean value depending on the truth value of both inputs.
They are &lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;not&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;print(True and True, False or False, not True)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-4-5-other-operators&#34;&gt;3.4.5 - Other operators&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other operators in Python, such as identity (&lt;code&gt;is&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;is not&lt;/code&gt;) or membership (&lt;code&gt;in&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;not in&lt;/code&gt;).
I am 100% sure you will be able to guess what is their effect on variables/containers!
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note this subtle difference between &lt;code&gt;==&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;is&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;==&lt;/code&gt; tests whether objects have the same value, whereas &lt;code&gt;is&lt;/code&gt;
tests whether objects have the same identity. Try it with &lt;code&gt;a=[1,2]&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;b=[1,2]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-5-sequences-and-object-containers&#34;&gt;3.5 - Sequences and Object Containers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-5-1-python-sequences&#34;&gt;3.5.1 - Python Sequences&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sequence is an &lt;strong&gt;ordered&lt;/strong&gt; collection of objects. In Python, you can find three types of sequences: Lists, Tuples, and Range Objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us focus on the first two of them. Lists and tuples can be accessed by indexing and can be sliced in several ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# A tuple
t = (0,True)
# A list l
l = [0,True]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that there is a relevant difference between tuples and lists: tuples are &lt;strong&gt;immutable&lt;/strong&gt;, while lists are not.
This means that you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to modify the content stored at &lt;code&gt;t&lt;/code&gt;. We will explain this in a second.
Note also that both lists and tuples allow you to mix different data types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;note-mutable-and-immutable-objects&#34;&gt;Note: Mutable and immutable objects&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of some objects can change in the course of program execution.
Objects whose value can change are said to be mutable objects,
whereas objects whose value is unchangeable after they&amp;rsquo;ve been created
are called immutable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing with sequences, in order to access the elements that a tuple/list holds, you use &lt;strong&gt;square brackets, not parenthesis&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# the first element of the tuple t
t_first = t[0]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also note that, the same as e.g. C (and different from e.g. Matlab), &lt;strong&gt;in Python indexing starts at 0&lt;/strong&gt;.
Be careful with this, because it is a common source of confusion in the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sequences can be accessed by indexing, which supports negatives indexes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;t = (0,1,&#39;hola&#39;,3,4.0)
l = [0,1,&#39;hola&#39;,3,4.0]
print(t[0])
print(t[-1]) # note the behavior of negative indexes
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sequences also support a very handy operation called &lt;strong&gt;slicing&lt;/strong&gt;, that enables access to multiple objects at the same time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;print(t[0:2]) # slicing first two elements, third is excluded
print(l[2:5]) # slicing last three elements
print(l[2:]) # empty spot after : means up to length-of-list index
print(l[:2]) # empty spot before : means from first index
print(l[0:5:2]) # every element, but use a step size of 2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuples and lists, as every python object, have several methods that you can use with them.
However, since lists are mutable, they have methods that can modify their content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;a = [4,3,2,1]
a.append(5)
print(a)
a.sort()
print(a)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that list methods are &lt;strong&gt;in-place methods&lt;/strong&gt;, they modify the original object that called them and return nothing.
For a complete list of these, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://faculty.salina.k-state.edu/tim/NPstudy_guide/python/containers.html#list-methods&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other generic Python functions that work with sequences and provide useful operations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;a = [4,3,2,1]
b = sorted(a)
n = len(b)
s = sum(a)
print(b, n, s)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-5-2-object-containers-dictionaries&#34;&gt;3.5.2 - Object Containers: Dictionaries&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sequences are a particularly simple example of Object Containers.
More generally, Python offers several more advanced object containers. A really useful one are dictionaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dictionaries are &lt;strong&gt;unordered sequences&lt;/strong&gt; that associate key objects to value objects.
This means that a dictionary consists of &lt;strong&gt;Key:Value&lt;/strong&gt; pairs, and the keys must be immutable while the values can be anything.
Note that dictionaries themselves are mutable objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dictionary is built with curly braces as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;ages = {&amp;quot;Me&amp;quot;: 33, &amp;quot;You&amp;quot;: 22, &amp;quot;Him&amp;quot;:24}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If now I want to know your age, and then increase it, I would type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;print(ages[&amp;quot;You&amp;quot;])
ages[&amp;quot;You&amp;quot;] += 1
print(ages[&amp;quot;You&amp;quot;])
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can add new items to your dictionary as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;ages[&amp;quot;Her&amp;quot;] = 20
print(ages)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dictionary objects have also their own methods.
For instance, you can use &lt;code&gt;keys&lt;/code&gt; to find out what are all the keys in the dictionary, or the &lt;code&gt;values&lt;/code&gt; method
to retrieve are all of the values in the dictionary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;names = ages.keys()
years = ages.values()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-6-python-typing&#34;&gt;3.6 - Python typing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Objects in Python are composed by their name, their content, and a reference that points the name to the content.
When an object is created, Python tells the computer to reserve memory locations to store the corresponding data.
Depending on the data type of a variable, the interpreter allocates a certain amount of memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have seen above, in Python, there is no need of declaring objects nor their type before using them.
This is because actually what you are doing is not creating a spot in memory and filling it with an object.
Rather, you are creating a pointer (that occupies a first memory spot), and then making that pointer point to an object in a second memory spot.
For this reason, you can for instance reassign a variable to a different type of object without errors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;a = [0,1,2]
a = (-1,3)
a = True
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that when you assign a variable to another, you are just creating a second pointer to that same memory spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;a = [0,1,2]
b = a
b[2] = 0
print(a)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-7-flow-control&#34;&gt;3.7 Flow Control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical flow control structures are implemented as usual in Python.
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Be careful with Python code &lt;strong&gt;indentation&lt;/strong&gt;:
the space you leave to the left of your piece of code implicitly delimits code blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

We will learn the behavior of flow control statements in Python by example,
to reinforce the idea of how intuitive Python is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-7-1-if-else-statements&#34;&gt;3.7.1 - &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;-&lt;code&gt;else&lt;/code&gt; statements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observe the following code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;if 3&amp;gt;2:
    print(&#39;success&#39;)
elif 3==2:
    print(&#39;failure&#39;)
else:
    print(&#39;I do not know&#39;)
print(&#39;This will be printed either way&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Do not forget about the semicolon in the end of control statements!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-7-2-for-loops&#34;&gt;3.7.2 - &lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt; loops&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observe the following code and try to predict its output:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;for i in [0,1,2,3]:
    print(i)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-7-3-while-loops&#34;&gt;3.7.3 - &lt;code&gt;while&lt;/code&gt; loops&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observe the following code and try to predict its output:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;i=0
while i &amp;lt; 4:
    print(i)
    i = i+1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-7-4-other-statements-break-and-continue&#34;&gt;3.7.4 - Other statements: &lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;continue&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observe the following two pieces of code and try to predict their output:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;for i in [1,2,3,4,5,6,7]:
    if i % 3 == 0:
        continue
    print(i)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;for i in [1,2,3,4,5,6,7]:
    if i % 3 == 0:
        break
    print(i)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Can you give a definition of both statements based on these experiments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-8-python-functions&#34;&gt;3.8 Python Functions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being only able to ``interactively&amp;rdquo; play with variables is boring.
To build more complex code, we need functions.
Functions are tools for grouping statements so that they can be executed more than once in the same program.
They are useful maximize code reuse and minimize code redundancy, therefore contributing to avoid errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functions are written using the &lt;code&gt;def&lt;/code&gt; statement.
You can send objects created inside your function back to where it was called with the &lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt; statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;def compute_sum(a,b):
    c = a+b
    return c
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use this function, we simply call it passing appropriate parameters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;a = 5
b = -2
print(compute_sum(a,b))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguments to Python functions are matched by position.
Tuples are typically used to return multiple values.
Note that functions themselves are objects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;print(type(compute_sum))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, variables created or assigned in a function are local of that function and exist only while the function runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;L = [0,1,2]
def modify(my_list):
    c = 3
    my_list[0] += 20
modify(L)
print(L)
print(c)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also possible to specify a &lt;strong&gt;default&lt;/strong&gt; value for some argument:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;def compute_sum(a,b=2):
    c = a+b
    return c
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, you can have keyword arguments.
A keyword argument is an argument which is supplied to the function by explicitly naming each parameter and specifying its value:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;print(1, 2, 3, 4, sep=&#39;;&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keyword arguments must always go behind non-keyword arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-9-classes-and-object-oriented-programming&#34;&gt;3.9 Classes and Object-Oriented Programming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can you go beyond built-in data types and create &lt;strong&gt;new object types&lt;/strong&gt;, with their
associated methods and attributes defined by you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python allows you to create new classes, and then define (&lt;em&gt;instantiate&lt;/em&gt;)
new objects of that class and interact with them. This way, you can
group data and functions operating on it in a more abstract way, and
then instantiate concrete samples and use them.
Classes allow for a simplified modeling of our problems, and enables the
creation of cleaner code that will be more easily extended in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When dealing with classes, data is usually called &lt;em&gt;attributes&lt;/em&gt;, and functions &lt;em&gt;methods&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-9-2-building-a-new-class-from-scratch&#34;&gt;3.9.2 - Building a new Class from scratch&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every class needs to have a special method, called &lt;code&gt;constructor&lt;/code&gt;, that initializes its attributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class UP_student:
    def __init__(self, name, math_skills, coding_skills, hard_working, theory_mark, practical_mark):
        self.name = name
        self.math_skills = math_skills
        self.coding_skills = coding_skills
        self.hard_working = hard_working                
        self.theory_mark = theory_mark
        self.practical_mark = practical_mark  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will note the presence of the &lt;code&gt;self&lt;/code&gt; parameter: this is a special inner
reference to the object state. It may take some time to understand the use
of &lt;code&gt;self&lt;/code&gt;, but do not be afraid, we will see some examples afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it stands, an object of the &lt;code&gt;UP_student&lt;/code&gt; class has very limited value, as it contains only data (attributes).
Let us add some spice by giving our class a function (method):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class Y:
    def __init__(self, v0):
        self.v0 = v0
        self.g = 9.81
    def value(self, t):
        return self.v0 * t - 0.5*self.g*t**2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The utility of &lt;code&gt;self&lt;/code&gt; starts to become clear now. At this point, you have
created a useful class, and you can instantiate an object of this new type easily:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;name = &#39;adrian_galdran&#39;
adrian_math_skills = 0.9
adrian_coding_skills = 0.8
adrian_hard_working = True
adrian_student = UP_student(name, adrian_math_skills, adrian_coding_skills, adrian_hard_working)
print(type(a_student))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, we call our class as if it was a normal Python function, and Python automatically invokes the constructor method.
&lt;code&gt;__init__&lt;/code&gt; requires several parameters to be specified at instantiation time. If you do not specify them correctly, you will get an error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, attributes and methods are exposed to the user:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;print(adrian_student.coding_skills)
print(adrian_student.hard_working)
print(&#39;Global Mark: &#39;, adrian_student.compute_global_mark(0.2)) # Let us give more weight to the practical part!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can you add new methods to your class? For instance, we can add a &lt;code&gt;print_global_mark&lt;/code&gt; method
that computes and prints the final mark automatically. This method only needs as input parameter &lt;code&gt;theory_weight&lt;/code&gt;, and outputs a string:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class UP_student:
    def __init__(self, name, math_skills, coding_skills, hard_working, theory_mark = 5, practical_mark = 4):
        self.name = name
        self.math_skills = math_skills
        self.coding_skills = coding_skills
        self.hard_working = hard_working                
        self.theory_mark = theory_mark
        self.practical_mark = practical_mark 
    def compute_global_mark(self, theory_weight = 0.6):
        return theory_weight*self.theory_mark + (1-theory_weight)*self.practical_mark
    def print_global_mark(self, theory_weight = 0.6):
        global_mark = self.compute_global_mark(theory_weight)
        print(&#39;The final mark of &#39;, self.name, &#39; is &#39;, global_mark)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that even if the &lt;code&gt;print_global_mark&lt;/code&gt; method only needs the &lt;code&gt;theory_weight&lt;/code&gt; argument, we still
must add the &lt;code&gt;self&lt;/code&gt; argument so that it can call &lt;code&gt;self.global_mark&lt;/code&gt;.
This is omitted in the method call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice also that inside the class, &lt;code&gt;compute_global_mark&lt;/code&gt; is known to the object and needs no &lt;code&gt;self&lt;/code&gt; parameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;name = &#39;adrian_galdran&#39;
adrian_math_skills = 0.9
adrian_coding_skills = 0.8
adrian_hard_working = True
adrian_student = UP_student(name, adrian_math_skills, adrian_coding_skills, adrian_hard_working)

adrian_student.print_global_mark()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know an object consists of both internal data and methods that perform operations on the data.
At some point you may find that existing object types do not fully suit your needs.
Classes are the tool that allows you to create new types of objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-9-2-class-inheritance&#34;&gt;3.9.2 - Class Inheritance&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, even if you have the need for a new type, it may happen that this new object type resembles,
in some way, an existing one.
Classes have the ability to inherit from other classes, and this is a fundamental aspect of OOP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us see an example of how to build a new class, inheriting from the built-in Python &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt; class.
We will add more functionality to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class MyList(list):
    
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this definition ensure that our new class, derived from &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt;, will inherit the attributes of the base class.
However, now we can extend, or redefine those attributes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, we are going to improve the built-in &lt;code&gt;remove&lt;/code&gt; methods, implemented by Python for lists in this way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;L = [0,1,2,5,5]
L.remove(5)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will add new methods to also be able to remove the maximum and minimum element of a list.
For this, we complete the definition of our extended class as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class MyList(list):
    def remove_min(self):
        self.remove(min(self))
    def remove_max(self):
        self.remove(max(self))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we can make use of our class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;L2 = MyList(L)
dir(L)
dir(L2)
print(L2.remove_min())
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-complementary-python-scientific-computing-tools-numpy&#34;&gt;4. &lt;strong&gt;Complementary Python Scientific Computing Tools: Numpy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the introduction, one of the most important strengths of Python is the large ecosystem of tools available.
One of the most important libraries for scientific computing in general (and for this course in particular) is &lt;strong&gt;NumPy&lt;/strong&gt;,
which is designed to perform matrix computations.
Here you will learn the fundamental concepts related to Numpy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-1-introduction-to-numpy-arrays&#34;&gt;4.1 - Introduction to NumPy Arrays&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python allows you to create nested lists, that you could use to work with n-dimensional arrays:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;zero_matrix = [[0,0,0],[0,0,0]]
print(len(zero_matrix),len(zero_matrix[0]))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, you can see this is quite inconvenient, and complexity will grow a lot with high dimensions.
Also, Python lists are not designed for linear algebra. For instance, &lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt; acting on lists means concatenation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;print([1,2]+[0,0])
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NumPy arrays are n-dimensional array objects which conform the core component of scientific computing in Python.
They are an additional data type provided by NumPy for representing vectors and matrices.
Unlike Python lists, elements of NumPy arrays are all of the same data type, and their size is fixed once defined.
By default, the elements are floating point numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a first example of how to build a vector and a matrix with all elements zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;import numpy as np

zero_vector = np.zeros(4)
zero_matrix = np.zeros((2,3))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that in the matrix case, we need to specify the dimensions through a tuple.
In order to build an array of ones, you can use the &lt;code&gt;numpy.ones&lt;/code&gt; function, with the same syntax:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;ones_matrix = np.ones((3,2))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, you can manually initialize them using &lt;code&gt;np.array&lt;/code&gt; and a Python list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;my_matrix = np.array([[2,1],[3,2],[5,4]])
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; supports the usual standard matrix operations, such as matrix transposition;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;my_transposed_matrix = my_matrix.transpose()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arithmetic operations work as expected also:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;my_matrix + ones_matrix
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that unlike MATLAB, &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; is elementwise multiplication, not matrix multiplication.
You need to use the &lt;code&gt;dot&lt;/code&gt; function to compute products of vectors, to multiply a vector by a matrix, and to multiply matrices.
&lt;code&gt;dot&lt;/code&gt; is available both as a function in the numpy module and as an instance method of array objects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = np.array([[1,2],[3,4]]) # 2x2 Matrix
y = np.array([[5,6],[7,8]]) # 2x2 Matrix

v = np.array([9,10]) # 1x2 vector
w = np.array([11, 12]) # 1x2 vector

# Matrix / vector product; both produce a 1x2 vector
print(x.dot(v))
print(np.dot(x, v))

# Matrix / matrix product; both produce a 2x2 matrix
# [[19 22]
#  [43 50]]
print(x.dot(y))
print(np.dot(x, y))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, you can find out the dimensions of a given &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; array through its &lt;code&gt;shape&lt;/code&gt; data attribute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;print(my_matrix.shape)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-2-slicing-numpy-arrays&#34;&gt;4.2 - Slicing NumPy Arrays&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same way you can slice Python lists, you can do the same with &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; arrays.
Remember the indexing logic.
Start index is included but stop index is not, so &lt;code&gt;Python&lt;/code&gt; stops just before it reaches the stop index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;my_first_column = my_matrix[:,0]
my_last_row = my_matrix[-1,:]
print(my_first_column.shape)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-3-indexing-numpy-arrays&#34;&gt;4.3 - Indexing NumPy Arrays&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NumPy arrays can also be indexed with other arrays or other sequence-like objects like lists. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;z1 = np.array([2,4,6,8,10])
z2 = z1+1
indexes_arr = np.array([0,1])
indexes_list = [0, 4]
print(z2, z2[indexes_arr], z2[indexes_list])
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way of indexing &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; arrays is with logical indices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;indexes_logical = [True, True, True, False, False]
print(z2[indexes_logical])
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note the potential of this operation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;print(z2&amp;gt;5)
print(z2[z2&amp;gt;5])
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;important-difference-between-slicing-and-indexing&#34;&gt;Important difference between slicing and indexing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you slice an array with the colon operator, you obtain a &lt;strong&gt;view&lt;/strong&gt; of the object.
This means that if you modify that view, you will also modify the original array.
In contrast, when you index an array, what you obtain is a (new) object, a copy independent of the original one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;z1 = np.array([2,4,6,8,10])
w_view = z1[0:3] # sliced z1
print(z1)
print(w_view)
w_view[0] = 50
print(z1)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare the above code snippet with this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;z1 = np.array([2,4,6,8,10])
indexes = [0,1,2,3,4]
w_copy = z1[indexes] # indexed z1
print(z1)
print(w_copy)
w_copy[0] = 50
print(z1)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-4-other-numpy-arrays-manipulation-techniques&#34;&gt;4.4 - Other numpy arrays manipulation techniques&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt;, if you want to build an array with fixed start and end values, such that the other elements are uniformly
spaced between them, you can do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;np.linspace(0, 100, 10) # stop point is included
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already seen an example of the attribute &lt;code&gt;shape&lt;/code&gt; of a &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; array. You can also check the total &lt;code&gt;size&lt;/code&gt; of it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;my_matrix = np.array([[2,1],[3,2],[5,4]])
print(my_matrix.shape)
print(my_matrix.size)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that neither &lt;code&gt;shape&lt;/code&gt; nor &lt;code&gt;size&lt;/code&gt; are followed by a parenthesis.
This is because they are not method attributes for the &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; array class, but rather data attributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of handy logical operations that work on top of &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; arrays.
For instance, you often will want to check if any/all of the elements in an array verifies a given condition.
This can be accomplished with the methods &lt;code&gt;any()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;all()&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = np.random.random(10)
print(x)
print(np.any(x&amp;gt;0.5))
print(np.all(x&amp;gt;0.5))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, instead of using the Python &lt;code&gt;random&lt;/code&gt; library, we used the &lt;code&gt;numpy.random&lt;/code&gt; module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-complementary-python-scientific-computing-tools-matplotlib&#34;&gt;5. &lt;strong&gt;Complementary Python Scientific Computing Tools: Matplotlib&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matplotlib is the standard Python plotting library.
Even if &lt;code&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt; is a very large library, it contains a module called &lt;code&gt;pyplot&lt;/code&gt;.
Pyplot is a collection of functionalities that make matplotlib work in a similar way as Matlab.
In this course, we will use &lt;code&gt;pyplot&lt;/code&gt; for our data visualizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-1-basic-matplotlib-usage&#34;&gt;5.1 - &lt;strong&gt;Basic Matplotlib usage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us import it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;import matplotlib.pyplot as plt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most basic function inside &lt;code&gt;pyplot&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;code&gt;plot&lt;/code&gt;.
Its simplest use case takes only one argument, specifying  the y-axis values that are to be plotted.
In this case, each y-axis value is plotted against its corresponding index value on the x-axis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;y = np.random.random(10)
plt.plot(y)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use &lt;code&gt;plot&lt;/code&gt; outside the iPython shell, the plot is created but not shown.
To tell Python to show the plot, you just need to add &lt;code&gt;plt.show()&lt;/code&gt; to your code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you give to &lt;code&gt;plot&lt;/code&gt; two arguments, the first argument specifies the x-coordinates and the second the y-coordinates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = np.linspace(0,10,100)
y = np.cos(x)
plt.plot(x,y)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also supply a third argument to &lt;code&gt;plot&lt;/code&gt; in order to give some cosmetic specifications on your plot, like color, line type or marker.
They work with key-word arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = np.linspace(0,10,20)
y = np.cos(x)
plt.plot(x, y, &#39;ro-&#39;)
plt.show()
plt.plot(x, y, &#39;gs-&#39;, linewidth=5, markersize=15)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that in this case &lt;code&gt;plt.show()&lt;/code&gt; forces Python to show the first plot, which otherwise would be ommited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-2-plot-customization&#34;&gt;5.2 - &lt;strong&gt;Plot Customization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us see some more advanced plot customization techniques.
To add a legend to an already created (even if still not shown) plot, you can use &lt;code&gt;legend()&lt;/code&gt;, which takes a string as an argument:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = np.linspace(-3,3,20)
y = x**2
plt.plot(x, y, &#39;ro-&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to add information on which quantities are specified on each axis, you can do it as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = np.linspace(-3,3,20)
y = x**2
plt.plot(x, y, &#39;ro-&#39;)
plt.xlabel(&#39;The x axis&#39;)
plt.ylabel(&#39;The y axis&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also customize what part of your plot you want to display with &lt;code&gt;axis()&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = np.linspace(-3,3,20)
y = x**2
plt.plot(x, y, &#39;ro-&#39;)
plt.axis([-0.5, 2, -2, 4]) #xmin, xmax, ymin, ymax
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also quite easy to overlay several plots:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = np.linspace(-3,3,20)
y1 = x**2
y2 = x**3
plt.plot(x, y1, &#39;ro-&#39;)
plt.plot(x,y2, &#39;b+-&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need to add an independent legend to each of these, you need to label each of them separately:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = np.linspace(-3,3,20)
y1 = x**2
y2 = x**3
plt.plot(x, y1, &#39;ro-&#39;, label = &#39;square&#39;)
plt.plot(x,y2, &#39;b+-&#39;, label = &#39;cubic&#39;)
plt.legend(loc = &#39;upper left&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;code&gt;legend()&lt;/code&gt; can take a keyword argument specifying location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, to save your figure, you simple use &lt;code&gt;savefig&lt;/code&gt;.
The extension of the file name you choose will determine the format of the output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = np.linspace(-3,3,20)
y1 = x**2
plt.plot(x, y1, &#39;ro-&#39;, label = &#39;square&#39;)
plt.savefig(&#39;my_plot.png&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, let us illustrate the use of histogram plotting tools in matplotlib, as well as how to build several subplots in the same plot.
First, we create a normally distributed array of numbers around zero using numpy as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = np.random.normal(size = 1000)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To build a histogram plot in pyplot we type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;plt.hist(x)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you want to plot the same histogram with two different colors in two different subplots, you can use the &lt;code&gt;plt.subplot()&lt;/code&gt; function.
This function takes three arguments: the first two specify the number of rows and columns in the subplot, and the third one is the plot number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;plt.subplot(1,2,1)
plt.hist(x, color = &#39;r&#39;);
plt.subplot(1,2,2)
plt.hist(x, color = &#39;b&#39;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note the use of a semicolon after each plot execution, in order to avoid printing the value returned by &lt;code&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;6-sources-and-references&#34;&gt;6. &lt;strong&gt;Sources and References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are tons of wonderful Python resources in the internet.
The main sources I used to build this lecture were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jake Van der Plas&amp;rsquo; book &lt;em&gt;A Whilrwind Tour of Python&lt;/em&gt;, available &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oreilly.com/programming/free/files/a-whirlwind-tour-of-python.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
in pdf, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jakevdp/WhirlwindTourOfPython&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; in iPython notebook format.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Harvard&amp;rsquo;s online course &lt;em&gt;Using Python for Research&lt;/em&gt;, hosted at &lt;a href=&#34;https://courses.edx.org/courses/course-v1:HarvardX+PH526x+3T2016/course/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;edX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stanford&amp;rsquo;s CS231n short Python tutorial &lt;a href=&#34;http://cs231n.github.io/python-numpy-tutorial/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, most of the material and presentation is shamelessly inspired in 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding the &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; part, if you are a Matlab user, you could find this resource very useful:
- Numpy for Matlab users - &lt;a href=&#34;http://scipy.github.io/old-wiki/pages/NumPy_for_Matlab_Users&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need or want more practice with Python and the tools presented today, I would recommend following the free course
at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.datacamp.com/courses/intro-to-python-for-data-science&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;datacamp&lt;/a&gt;, and doing all the exercises proposed there.
Codeacademy exercises, hosted &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codecademy.com/learn/learn-python&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, can also be very useful to get more experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DACO - Practical Lecture 2 - Bayesian Classification and Linear Regression</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_2/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Where we introduce the scikit-learn library for Machine Learning.
We will code from scratch a Naive Bayes classifier and a Linear Regressor,
and compare them with sk-learn implementations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year we have decided to move from Matlab to Python for the practical sessions.
Some of you maybe will not have worked with this programming language.
This first lecture is intended to make you aware of the (super-rich) Python ecosystem for scientific computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really hope that by the end of this course you will be a Python fan, and consider abandoning Matlab once and forever!
This is an overview of what you will be learning today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motivation and Goals. What is Python?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Python Installation. Accompanying Tools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Swift Introduction to the Python Programming Language&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Complementary Python Scientific Computing Tools&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Homework 😱&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sources and References&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So&amp;hellip; let&amp;rsquo;s move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-motivation-and-goals-what-is-python&#34;&gt;1.- &lt;strong&gt;Motivation and Goals. What is Python?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First thing, Python is &lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt;. Second, it is &lt;strong&gt;simple&lt;/strong&gt;.
Third, it is increasingly becoming the tool of choice for data science projects.
And last, there is a &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt; community of contributors to lots of open-source projects that complement it.
This manifests in the form of a large ecosystem of scientific computing tools that grow along with the number of users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, to add all this to your toolbelt, the first step is to familiarize yourself with the Python language itself.
Today we will quickly traverse the main notions to get started on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, let us install Python!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-python-installation-accompanying-tools&#34;&gt;2. &lt;strong&gt;Python Installation. Accompanying Tools.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conda/Anaconda. Command Line. Package Manager. IDEs. Ipython Notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-introduction-to-the-python-programming-language&#34;&gt;3. &lt;strong&gt;Introduction to the Python Programming Language&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;first&lt;/strong&gt;
The same as in any language, Python also has different types of data.
The same as in e.g Matlab (and different from e.g. C) you do not need to explicitly declare the type of a variable.
Python determines data type of variables by how they are used.
For instance, to create an integer (&lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt;) variable you simply type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# An integer variable a
a = 5
print(type(a))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;type&lt;/code&gt; are a built-in Python functions that behave as you would expect.
More on functions later.
Note that in Python 2 you would not use parentheses with &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt;
Other basic/common python types are for instance&lt;code&gt;float&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;boolean&lt;/code&gt;, exemplified below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# A float variable f
f = 5.0
# A boolean
b = True
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;second&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;third&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python has lots of operators, the most prominent ones being &lt;strong&gt;arithmetic&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;comparison&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;logical&lt;/strong&gt;.
&amp;ndash; Arithmetic operators will take two variables and perform simple mathematical operations on them.
They are addition, subtraction, multiplication, division, modulus, floor division, and exponentiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# A list of lists
l = [[0],[1],[2,3]]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Comparison operators observe two variables and return a boolean value.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fusion-Based Variational Image Dehazing</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/publication/fvid_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/publication/fvid_2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Detailed instructions to run the code are included in the downloaded zipped files.
Please note that we can provide limited support to any problem that may arise during execution of this code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pw for the zipped code is spl2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This software is provided &amp;ldquo;as is&amp;rdquo;, without warranty of any kind, express or implied, including but not limited to the warranties of merchantability, fitness for a particular purpose and noninfringement. In no event shall the authors or copyright holders be liable for any claim, damages or other liability, whether in an action of contract, tort or otherwise, arising from, out of or in connection with the software or the use or other dealings in the software.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embed your slides or video here using &lt;a href=&#34;https://gcushen.github.io/hugo-academic-demo/post/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Further details can easily be added using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/project/deep-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/project/deep-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Duis posuere tellus ac convallis placerat. Proin tincidunt magna sed ex sollicitudin condimentum. Sed ac faucibus dolor, scelerisque sollicitudin nisi. Cras purus urna, suscipit quis sapien eu, pulvinar tempor diam. Quisque risus orci, mollis id ante sit amet, gravida egestas nisl. Sed ac tempus magna. Proin in dui enim. Donec condimentum, sem id dapibus fringilla, tellus enim condimentum arcu, nec volutpat est felis vel metus. Vestibulum sit amet erat at nulla eleifend gravida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nullam vel molestie justo. Curabitur vitae efficitur leo. In hac habitasse platea dictumst. Sed pulvinar mauris dui, eget varius purus congue ac. Nulla euismod, lorem vel elementum dapibus, nunc justo porta mi, sed tempus est est vel tellus. Nam et enim eleifend, laoreet sem sit amet, elementum sem. Morbi ut leo congue, maximus velit ut, finibus arcu. In et libero cursus, rutrum risus non, molestie leo. Nullam congue quam et volutpat malesuada. Sed risus tortor, pulvinar et dictum nec, sodales non mi. Phasellus lacinia commodo laoreet. Nam mollis, erat in feugiat consectetur, purus eros egestas tellus, in auctor urna odio at nibh. Mauris imperdiet nisi ac magna convallis, at rhoncus ligula cursus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cras aliquam rhoncus ipsum, in hendrerit nunc mattis vitae. Duis vitae efficitur metus, ac tempus leo. Cras nec fringilla lacus. Quisque sit amet risus at ipsum pharetra commodo. Sed aliquam mauris at consequat eleifend. Praesent porta, augue sed viverra bibendum, neque ante euismod ante, in vehicula justo lorem ac eros. Suspendisse augue libero, venenatis eget tincidunt ut, malesuada at lorem. Donec vitae bibendum arcu. Aenean maximus nulla non pretium iaculis. Quisque imperdiet, nulla in pulvinar aliquet, velit quam ultrices quam, sit amet fringilla leo sem vel nunc. Mauris in lacinia lacus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suspendisse a tincidunt lacus. Curabitur at urna sagittis, dictum ante sit amet, euismod magna. Sed rutrum massa id tortor commodo, vitae elementum turpis tempus. Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Aenean purus turpis, venenatis a ullamcorper nec, tincidunt et massa. Integer posuere quam rutrum arcu vehicula imperdiet. Mauris ullamcorper quam vitae purus congue, quis euismod magna eleifend. Vestibulum semper vel augue eget tincidunt. Fusce eget justo sodales, dapibus odio eu, ultrices lorem. Duis condimentum lorem id eros commodo, in facilisis mauris scelerisque. Morbi sed auctor leo. Nullam volutpat a lacus quis pharetra. Nulla congue rutrum magna a ornare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aliquam in turpis accumsan, malesuada nibh ut, hendrerit justo. Cum sociis natoque penatibus et magnis dis parturient montes, nascetur ridiculus mus. Quisque sed erat nec justo posuere suscipit. Donec ut efficitur arcu, in malesuada neque. Nunc dignissim nisl massa, id vulputate nunc pretium nec. Quisque eget urna in risus suscipit ultricies. Pellentesque odio odio, tincidunt in eleifend sed, posuere a diam. Nam gravida nisl convallis semper elementum. Morbi vitae felis faucibus, vulputate orci placerat, aliquet nisi. Aliquam erat volutpat. Maecenas sagittis pulvinar purus, sed porta quam laoreet at.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>External Project</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/project/example-external-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/project/example-external-project/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Person Re-Identification System For Mobile Devices</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/publication/person-re-identification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/publication/person-re-identification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More detail can easily be written here using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobile visual clothing search</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/publication/clothing-search/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/publication/clothing-search/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More detail can easily be written here using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_1_old/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_1_old/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;EXERCISES:
&lt;strong&gt;Homework&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Protect data from the user (i.e. you!).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class Person(object):
    def __init__(self, name, mobile_phone=None, office_phone=None, private_phone=None, email=None):
        self.name = name
        self.mobile = mobile_phone
        self.office = office_phone
        self.private = private_phone
        self.email = email

    def add_mobile_phone(self, number):
        self.mobile = number
    def add_office_phone(self, number):
        self.office = number
    def add_private_phone(self, number):
        self.private = number
    def add_email(self, address):
        self.email = address
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note the use of None as default value for various data attributes: the object None
is commonly used to indicate that a variable or attribute is defined, but yet not with
a sensible value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-homework&#34;&gt;5. &lt;strong&gt;Homework 😱&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what I want you to do for next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;review-exercises-mandatory&#34;&gt;Review exercises (mandatory)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can find some exercises to review the concepts explained up to now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;numpy-mandatory&#34;&gt;Numpy (mandatory)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can find some exercises to review the concepts explained up to now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dictionaries-mandatory&#34;&gt;Dictionaries (mandatory)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explanation of what a dictionary is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can find some exercises for dictionaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;classes-mandatory&#34;&gt;Classes (mandatory)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explanation of how classes work in Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can find some exercises for classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;debugging-in-python-recommended&#34;&gt;Debugging in Python (recommended)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explanation of how to handle exceptions. Look into page 45 of JvdP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can find some exercises for exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;iterators-recommended&#34;&gt;Iterators (recommended)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we saw the example of a for loop, the looping variable traversed a list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;for i in [0,1,2,3]:
    print(i)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, the object to the right of &lt;code&gt;in&lt;/code&gt; needs to be an &lt;code&gt;iterator&lt;/code&gt;.
A &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt; is a special type of &lt;code&gt;iterator&lt;/code&gt;.
These can be understood as generalized sequences, and will be important in following lectures.
See page 52 of VdP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can find some exercises for iterators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;generators-recommended&#34;&gt;Generators (recommended)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can find some exercises for generators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;kwargs-and-kwargs-recommended&#34;&gt;*kwargs and **kwargs (recommended)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following code:
```python4.- We are going to count the frequency of each letter in a given string.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.1) import the &lt;code&gt;string&lt;/code&gt; library.
Now create a variable &lt;code&gt;alphabet&lt;/code&gt; that consists of the lowercase and uppercase letters in the English alphabet. For this,
use the `ascii_lett4.- We are going to count the frequency of each letter in a given string.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.1) import the &lt;code&gt;string&lt;/code&gt; library.
Now create a variable &lt;code&gt;alphabet&lt;/code&gt; that consists of the lowercase and uppercase letters in the English alphabet. For this,
use the &lt;code&gt;ascii_letters&lt;/code&gt; attribute of the string library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.2) Now, consider the sentence &amp;lsquo;Jim quickly realized that the beautiful gowns are expensive&amp;rsquo;.
Create a dictionary &lt;code&gt;count_letters&lt;/code&gt; with keys consisting of each unique letter in the sentence and values consisting of
the number of times each letter is used in this sentence.
Count both upper case and lower case letters separately in the dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hint: You can loop (&lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt;) over each letter in your sentence, check (&lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;) if the letter is already among your dictionary keys, and otherwise, update your dictionary with a new key.
For that, you can count the number of occurrences with the method &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt;, which you can look up in google.
Do not forget to omit the blank space in &lt;code&gt;sentence&lt;/code&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.3) Use the code you built in 4.2) to create a function called &lt;code&gt;counter&lt;/code&gt; that takes a string &lt;code&gt;input_string&lt;/code&gt; and returns
a dictionary of letter counts &lt;code&gt;count_letters&lt;/code&gt;. Test it with &lt;code&gt;sentence&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.4) Use the dictionary created by your function to find out and print the most frequent letter in &lt;code&gt;sentence&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5.- The distance between two points &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt; is the square root of the sum of squared differences along each dimension of &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt;.
Build a function &lt;code&gt;distance(x, y)&lt;/code&gt; that takes two vectors and outputs the distance between them.
Use your function to find the distance between &lt;code&gt;x=(0,0)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;y=(1,1)&lt;/code&gt;, and between &lt;code&gt;x=(0,0,0)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;y=(1,1,1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hint: To be able to take the square root, import the &lt;code&gt;math&lt;/code&gt; library. ers` attribute of the string library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.2) Now, consider the sentence &amp;lsquo;Jim quickly realized that the beautiful gowns are expensive&amp;rsquo;.
Create a dictionary &lt;code&gt;count_letters&lt;/code&gt; with keys consisting of each unique letter in the sentence and values consisting of
the number of times each letter is used in this sentence.
Count both upper case and lower case letters separately in the dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hint: You can loop (&lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt;) over each letter in your sentence, check (&lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;) if the letter is already among your dictionary keys, and otherwise, update your dictionary with a new key.
For that, you can count the number of occurrences with the method &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt;, which you can look up in google.
Do not forget to omit the blank space in &lt;code&gt;sentence&lt;/code&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.3) Use the code you built in 4.2) to create a function called &lt;code&gt;counter&lt;/code&gt; that takes a string &lt;code&gt;input_string&lt;/code&gt; and returns
a dictionary of letter counts &lt;code&gt;count_letters&lt;/code&gt;. Test it with &lt;code&gt;sentence&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.4) Use the dictionary created by your function to find out and print the most frequent letter in &lt;code&gt;sentence&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5.- The distance between two points &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt; is the square root of the sum of squared differences along each dimension of &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt;.
Build a function &lt;code&gt;distance(x, y)&lt;/code&gt; that takes two vectors and outputs the distance between them.
Use your function to find the distance between &lt;code&gt;x=(0,0)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;y=(1,1)&lt;/code&gt;, and between &lt;code&gt;x=(0,0,0)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;y=(1,1,1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hint: To be able to take the square root, import the &lt;code&gt;math&lt;/code&gt; library.
a=[1,2,3]
a[1]=4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;What is a?
1.- This code contains an error 2.- [1,2,3] 3.- etc.
### 2
Consider the following code:
```python
a=(1,2,3)
a[1]=4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is a?
1.- This code contains an error 2.- [1,2,3] 3.- etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = &amp;quot;Hello, world!&amp;quot;
y = x[5:]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the value of y?
1.- This code contains an error 2.- &amp;lsquo;Hello&amp;rsquo; 3.- etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following code and output:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = 1
def my_function():
  x = 2
  print(x)
print(x)
my_function()
print(x)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will be printed?
1.- 1;2;1
2.- 2;2;2
3.- 1;2;2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explanation: x is first defined globally, with value 1. Then, my_function
creates a variable x with local scope. Therefore, its value does not extend beyond its use in the function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;import math
print(math.cos(math.pi))
-1.0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What type of object is math.pi? And math.cos?
int, float, function, string&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say you want to flip a coin until you get 10 heads. Should you use
a for loop or while loop?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say you want to flip a coin 10 times and count the number of heads.
Should you use a for loop or a while loop?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following code and output:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;x = 1
while x &amp;lt; 5:
  x *= 2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the final value of x?
8&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.- We are going to count the frequency of each letter in a given string.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.1) import the &lt;code&gt;string&lt;/code&gt; library.
Now create a variable &lt;code&gt;alphabet&lt;/code&gt; that consists of the lowercase and uppercase letters in the English alphabet. For this,
use the &lt;code&gt;ascii_letters&lt;/code&gt; attribute of the string library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.2) Now, consider the sentence &amp;lsquo;Jim quickly realized that the beautiful gowns are expensive&amp;rsquo;.
Create a dictionary &lt;code&gt;count_letters&lt;/code&gt; with keys consisting of each unique letter in the sentence and values consisting of
the number of times each letter is used in this sentence.
Count both upper case and lower case letters separately in the dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hint: You can loop (&lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt;) over each letter in your sentence, check (&lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;) if the letter is already among your dictionary keys, and otherwise, update your dictionary with a new key.
For that, you can count the number of occurrences with the method &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt;, which you can look up in google.
Do not forget to omit the blank space in &lt;code&gt;sentence&lt;/code&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.3) Use the code you built in 4.2) to create a function called &lt;code&gt;counter&lt;/code&gt; that takes a string &lt;code&gt;input_string&lt;/code&gt; and returns
a dictionary of letter counts &lt;code&gt;count_letters&lt;/code&gt;. Test it with &lt;code&gt;sentence&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.4) Use the dictionary created by your function to find out and print the most frequent letter in &lt;code&gt;sentence&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5.- The distance between two points &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt; is the square root of the sum of squared differences along each dimension of &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt;.
Build a function &lt;code&gt;distance(x, y)&lt;/code&gt; that takes two vectors and outputs the distance between them.
Use your function to find the distance between &lt;code&gt;x=(0,0)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;y=(1,1)&lt;/code&gt;, and between &lt;code&gt;x=(0,0,0)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;y=(1,1,1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hint: To be able to take the square root, import the &lt;code&gt;math&lt;/code&gt; library.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
