<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Daco_prac_17 on Adrian Galdran - Research Site</title>
    <link>https://agaldran.github.io/tags/daco_prac_17/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Daco_prac_17 on Adrian Galdran - Research Site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Adrian Galdran</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://agaldran.github.io/tags/daco_prac_17/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>DACO 2017 Practical Lecs.</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/home/17_daco_practicals/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/home/17_daco_practicals/</guid>
      <description>Here you can find practical material for the Computer-Aided Diagnosis (DACO) course, taught at the Faculty of Engineering/University of Porto, in its 2017&amp;frasl;18 edition.
This year, I am the teaching instructor for the practical sessions, and I also teach some theory. Below you will find content associated to the practical lectures. I will probably be updating this each week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DACO - Practical Lecture 1 - Introduction to Python for Scientific Computing</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_1/</guid>
      <description>NOTE: pdf slides for the first part of this lecture can be found here
This year we have decided to move from Matlab to Python for the practical sessions. Some of you maybe will not have worked with this programming language. This first lecture is intended to guide you through your first steps in this programming language, and make you aware of the (super-rich) Python ecosystem for scientific computing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DACO - Practical Lecture 2 - Bayesian Classification and Linear Regression</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_2/</guid>
      <description>This practical lecture is again based on Jupyter Notebooks. You can see and download the notebook corresponding to today here. For completeness, please also download the following set of Python files, which will illustrate the use of Jupyter notebooks in combination with Spyder: [1], [2], [3]. Please store them in the same folder as where you put the notebook.
Note that we discuss Linear Regression in Theoretical Lecture 6. For this reason, we will only be using them alsmot as a black-box today, to familiarize ourselves with sk-learn for regression tasks.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>