<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Adrian Galdran - Research Site</title>
    <link>https://agaldran.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Adrian Galdran - Research Site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Adrian Galdran</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://agaldran.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>DACO - Practical Lecture 1 - Introduction to Python for Scientific Computing</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_1/</guid>
      <description>NOTE: pdf slides for the first part of this lecture can be found here
This year we have decided to move from Matlab to Python for the practical sessions. Some of you maybe will not have worked with this programming language. This first lecture is intended to guide you through your first steps in this programming language, and make you aware of the (super-rich) Python ecosystem for scientific computing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DACO - Practical Lecture 2 - Bayesian Classification and Linear Regression</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_prac_lec_2/</guid>
      <description>This practical lecture is again based on Jupyter Notebooks. You can see and download the notebook corresponding to today here. For completeness, please also download the following set of Python files, which will illustrate the use of Jupyter notebooks in combination with Spyder: [1], [2], [3]. Please store them in the same folder as where you put the notebook.
Note that we discuss Linear Regression in Theoretical Lecture 6. For this reason, we will only be using them alsmot as a black-box today, to familiarize ourselves with sk-learn for regression tasks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DACO - Theoretical Lecture 6a - Linear Models</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_theory_lec_6a/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_theory_lec_6a/</guid>
      <description>Today&amp;rsquo;s lecture is split in two parts.
In the first part, you will be introduced to a simple, but fundamental kind of machine learning models, Linear models. We will understand how are they formulated, and how can they be solved numerically. We will also see how can they be used for both regression and classification.
The second part comprises an introduction to non-linear models, specifically to neural networks. We will continue studying neural networks in the next lecture, but this week you will already understand what are they and how can they be used for classification tasks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DACO - Theoretical Lecture 6b - Introduction to Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_theory_lec_6b/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://agaldran.github.io/post/17_daco_theory_lec_6b/</guid>
      <description>Under construction.
See here for backpropagation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>